<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Interview on </title>
    <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/tags/interview/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Interview on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Olivier Gimenez</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/tags/interview/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiring interviews</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/post/interview_inra/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2015 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/post/interview_inra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was on a committee that hired 3 junior permanent researchers for INRA. Everything
went smoothly mostly due to the friendly atmosphere between people of the committee.
It had me thinking about what works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t work in job applications and
interviews. Here are my 2 cents suggestions, I&amp;rsquo;m sure you can find plenty of more
clever and relevant recommendations on the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In disorder, read and stick to the guidelines (not that obvious sometimes), and do
not hesitate to include figures and boxes in the document. Structure does not hurt,
well articulated sections are welcome. In contrast with CNRS, but like universities,
INRA hires people based on the quality of fit to profiles proposed by the INRA teams
(but it also has non-thematic positions), hence the importance to project yourself in
the team/lab where the researcher will be hosted, and the job itself. Have your applications
read by one or two colleagues, if possible someone who has experience in being on the
kind of hiring committee you will have to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the interview, appearances matter, whether you like it or not, therefore pick
something neutral and comfortable (my opinion). Don&amp;rsquo;t use slides with too much text
or complex figures (no tables please!), and point at your slides so that your visual
support is part of your speech. Don&amp;rsquo;t look at the screen or the walls, try to look at
the members of the jury. Occupy the space, don&amp;rsquo;t always stay at the same spot, but do not
move too much (I&amp;rsquo;m useless at that). Don’t rush when you talk, and give short answers
so that every member of the committee gets a chance to ask you a question. Be honest:
if you don&amp;rsquo;t know something, or if you don&amp;rsquo;t understand a question (which most likely
means that members of the hiring committee do not understand this question either),
say it. Last, but not least: rehearse, rehearse and rehearse again, there will be a
moment where you do no longer sound like you know your text by heart, but rather, like
saying it has become natural. From my experience, the round of questions is more
determinant than the talk itself, but we have very rare opportunities to train on
how to answer questions. Try to have sessions of questions with your colleagues to
get better at it; it comes with experience, no secret. For short talks, my advice is
to write your text, at least for the first slides so that you&amp;rsquo;re confident you won&amp;rsquo;t
get stuck when you start giving your speech.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My CNRS interview for a senior scientist position</title>
      <link>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/post/cnrs_interview/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://oliviergimenez.github.io/post/cnrs_interview/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are the slides of my interview for a CNRS senior scientist position (DR2). Note that
CNRS offers interdisciplinary positions, which is sadly not true for all of our research
institutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://widgets.figshare.com/articles/4833104/embed?show_title=1&#34; width=&#34;568&#34; height=&#34;426&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
